Guide to the John Nolen Papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
Nolen, John papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John Nolen papers, 1890-1938, 1954-1960.
2903
Nolen, John,
135.9 cubic ft., 257 map case folders
Correspondence, Diaries, Manuscripts, Photographs, Printed Materials, Research Materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of personal and professional correspondence, letterbooks, addresses, biographical data, diaries, scrapbooks, school notes and textbooks, syllabi, lectures and outlines, typescript papers and articles, printed material, policy directives, card files, sample contracts, projects files and reports, slides, photographs, negatives, plans, blueprints, drawings, charts, and maps relating to Nolen's work in city planning, preservation, survey projects, zoning, and extension programs.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
City planner, landscape architect.
John Nolen attended the University of Pennsylvania, earning a Ph.D. in 1893, and for the next ten years worked as secretary of the American Society for the Extension of University Teaching. In 1903 he enrolled in the newly established Harvard School of Landscape Architecture, receiving an A.M. in 1905. He established an office in Cambridge, where he and his associates branched out into city planning as well as landscape architecture. Over the course of his career, Nolen participated in 400 public planning projects and works of landscape architecture, and replanned 50 cities in 20 states. Travel and field work were important aspects of his career. He used visual media, including glass slides, extensively. He was a frequent lecturer on city and town planning, and was active in many professional organizations, including the American City Planning Institute (later called the American Institute of Planners, now known as the American Planners Association), American Civic Association (now Urban America), American Society of Landscape Architects, American Society of Planning Officials, International Garden Cities and Town-Planning Federation, National Conference on City Planning (now Urban America), and the Town Planning Institute of England.
CHRONOLOGY
1869 Born June 14, Philadelphia, son of John C. and Mathilda (Thomas)
1878-1884 Girard College, Philadelphia
1885 Grocery clerk
1886-1891 Minor secretary, Girard Estate Trust Fund
1891-1893 University of Pennsylvania, Wharton School as economics and public administration major, degree of Bachelor of Philosophy
1893-1903 American Society for the Extension of University Teaching
1895 Travel to Europe; Oxford, England Summer Course
1896 Travel to Europe; April 22, married Barbara Schatte of Philadelphia; November, Secretary of the American Society for the Extension of University Teaching
1900 Travel to Europe
1900-1901 University of Munich
1903-1905 Harvard School of Landscape Architecture, Master of Arts
1904 Opened office, Harvard Square, Cambridge
1906 Travel to Europe
1911 Travel to Europe
1912 Member, Metropolitan Boston Planning Commission, visited Europe with Boston Chamber of Commerce party
1913 Honorary Doctor of Science degree, Hobart College, Geneva, N.Y.
1914 Travel to Europe
Judge of competition to rebuild Dublin
1923 Travel to Europe; arranges Gottenberg exhibit, Sweden; member of Committee on the Regional Plan of New York and Its Environs, associated with the Russell Sage Foundation. "….new experiment in planning method.
While economic and social investigators carry on their studies, a group of notable planners has been called together to guide and co-ordinate their investigations.
Thomas Adams ... chairman, John Nolen Harland Bartholomew, George B. Ford, Edward Bennett, co-worker of Daniel Burnham in the Chicago Plan and Frederick Law Olmsted."
1926 President, National Conference on City Planning; travel to Europe; September, International Housing and Town Planning Congress
1927 Travel to Europe, Town Planning Institute meeting, London, England
1928 Travel to Europe, International Housing and Town Planning Congress, Paris
1931 President, International Federation of Housing and Town Planning.
June 22, award by the Oberlaender Trust "to study the development of city planning in Germany, particularly the beautifying of river banks and water waterfronts"
June 5-28, Russia, 1st All Union convention on City Planning Open to Foreign Specialists
1932 President, Boston Society of Landscape Architects; May, visited International Congress of Local Authorities in London, and visited Germany
1933 President, Federated Societies on Planning Parks
1935 Presided over International Housing and Town Planning Conference, London
1937 Died, February 10, Cambridge, Massachusetts
GOVERNMENT CONSULTING
1918 Member, advisory housing committee, Emergency Fleet Corporation
Chief, Bureau of Housing and town Planning, Army Educational Committee
Town planner, Union Park Garden, U.S. Shipping Board
Niagara Falls project, U.S. Housing Corporation
1933 Since 1933, consultant in U.S. Department of Interior with assignments in National Park Service, National Resources Committee, Resettlement Administration (Greenbelt towns) and Housing Division, P.W.A.
State planning consultant for New Hampshire, Vermont, Alabama and East Georgia Planning Council
PUBLICATIONS
1907 Editor, Repton's Art of Landscape Gardening
1910 Madison, a Model City
1911-1912 Replanning Small Cities
1919 New Ideals in Planning of Cities, Towns and Villages
1927 New Towns for Old
1937 Obituary, Boston Herald "Recently he had been engaged in an extensive research of American parkways systems to be published as one of the Harvard city planning studies."
Nolen, John and Hubbard H.V., Parkways v. Land Values (Harvard City Planning Studies no. 11) Cambridge, Harvard University Press
ORGANIZATIONS
Fellow, American Society of Landscape Architects
Member, Board of Directors, American Planning and Civic Association (now Urban America Inc.)
Member, Board of Directors, American Society of Planning Officials (now A.P.A.)
Past president, National Conference on City Planning
Past president, American City Planning Institute (now A.I.P., which is part of A.P.A.)
Member, American Society of Civil Engineers
Member, American Federation of Arts
Member, Town Planning Institute, England
Member, Beta Theta Pi
Past president and member, Executive Committee, International Federation for Housing and Town Planning
President, Federated Societies on Planning and Parks
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of personal and professional correspondence, letterbooks, addresses, biographical data, diaries, scrapbooks, school notes and textbooks, syllabi, lectures and outlines, typescript papers and articles, printed material, policy directives, card files, sample contracts, projects files and reports, slides, photographs, negatives, plans, blueprints, drawings, charts, and maps relating to Nolen's work in city planning, preservation, survey projects, zoning, and extension programs. Includes records pertaining to Nolen's studies at the University of Pennsylvania and Harvard; his work at the American Society for the Extension of University Teaching; consulting jobs; projects with the United States Housing Corporation, National Resources Committee, National Park Service, National Resources Planning Board, Federal Emergency Relief Administration of Public Works, Resettlement Administration, Department of the Interior, Division of Subsistence Homesteads, and various city and state agencies; and housing, parks, streets, railways, and water systems in Bridgeport, Conn., Charlotte, N.C., Clearwater, Clewiston, Sarasota, and Venice, Fla., Columbus, Ga., Johnson City and Kingsport, Tenn., La Crosse and Madison, Wis., Lancaster and Reading, Pa., Little Rock, Ark., Mariemont, Ohio, Niagara Falls, N.Y., Riverton, N.J., Roanoke, Va., Sacramento and San Diego, Calif., Boston, Mass., Spartanburg, S.C., Dubuque, Iowa; and other places.
Includes correspondence from the Marchioness of Aberdeen, Thomas Adams, Captain S.B. Alexander, Philip R. Allen, Charles B. Ball, Edward M. Bassett, G. Frank Beer, George A. Bellamy, Russell Van Nest Black, Joshua L. Brooks, Helen E. Chase, Charles E. Cheney, Richard S. Childs, Herbert C. Chivers, Carlos Contreras, David Cushman Coyle, Jacob L. Crane, Jr., J. Benjamin Dimmick, Earle Sumner Draper, Mrs. Thomas A. Edison, Richard T. Ely, Robert E. Ely, F.F. Feidler, Edward A. Filene, Henry Ford, James Ford, Philip W. Foster, Kenneth E. Franzheim, George B. Gallup, Patrick Geddes, Edward Howard Griggs, Harry Highland, N.J. Hoggson, B.W. Huebsch, John Ihlder, Mrs. C.B. La Monte, J.E. Latham, Nelson P. Lewis, Arthur MacArthur, George H. Maxwell, Richard Meinig, John Nolen, Jr., Irving C. Root, Mrs. Robert M. Seymour, Clarence Stein, Raymond Unwin, Claude G. Varn, Hale J. Walker, Frank B. Williams, George Zug, American Institute of Architects, Babson Institute, Advisory Committee on Housing (Boston), Boston Metropolitan Planning Commission, Cleveland City Plan Commission, General Federation of Women's Clubs, Guggenheim Foundation, Massachusetts Dept. of Public Welfare, Massachusetts City League, Massachusetts Federation of Planning Boards, New England Council, New England Regional Planning Commission, New York Regional Plan Association, Philadelphia Regional Planning Federation, Russell Sage Foundation, and the Tennessee Valley Authority.
Also, "The Nolen Family Album: A Record of Five Generations 1835-1954," family history, compiled by John Nolen, Jr. and Barbara Nolen Strong, 1980.
Includes results of projects funded by John Nolen Research Fund, broadsides for Nolen exhibits and symposia, and other Nolen documentation.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Nolen, John, 1869-1937.; Adams, Thomas, 1871-1940.; Alexander, S. B.; Allen, Philip R.; Ball, Charles B.; Bassett, Edward M. (Edward Murray), 1863-1948.; Beer, G. Frank.; Bellamy, George Albert, 1872-1960.; Black, Russell Van Nest, 1893-1969.; Brooks, Joshua L.; Chase, Helen E.; Cheney, Charles E.; Childs, Richard S. (Richard Spencer), 1882-; Chivers, Herbert C.; Contreras, Carlos.; Coyle, David Cushman, 1887-1969.; Crane, Jacob L. (Jacob Leslie), 1892-1988.; Dimmick, J. Benjamin.; Draper, E. S. (Earle Sumner), 1893-1994.; Ely, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1854-1943.; Ely, Robert Erskine, 1861-; Feidler, F. F.; Filene, Edward A.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Ford, James, 1884-1944.; Foster, Philip W.; Franzheim, Kenneth, 1890-1959.; Gallup, George B.; Geddes, Patrick, Sir, 1854-1932.; Griggs, Edward Howard.; Hancock, John L.; Highland, Harry.; Hoggson, N. J.; Huebsch, B. W. (Benjamin W.), 1876-1964.; Ihlder, John, 1876-1958.; La Monte, C. B., Mrs.; Latham, J. E.; Lewis, Nelson Peter, 1856-1924.; MacArthur, Arthur.; Maxwell, George H.; Meinig, Richard.; Nolen, John, 1898-1986.; Root, Irving C.; Seymour, Robert M., Mrs.; Stein, Clarence S.; Unwin, Raymond, Sir, 1863-1940.; Varn, Claude G.; Walker, Hale J.; Williams, Frank B. (Frank Backus), 1864-1954.; Zug, George R., 1938-; American Civic Association.; American Institute of Architects.; American Institute of Planners.; American Society of Landscape Architects.; American Society of Planning Officials.; Babson Institute.; Boston (Mass.). Advisory Committee on Housing.; Boston Metropolitan Planning Commission.; City Housing Corporation.; Cleveland (Ohio). City Plan Commission.; Forest Park and Planning Association.; General Federation of Women's Clubs.; Harvard University -- Students.; International Federation for Housing and Planning.; International Garden Cities and Town-Planning Federation.; Massachusetts Civic League.; Massachusetts Federation of Planning Boards.; Massachusetts. Department of Public Welfare.; National Conference on City Planning.; National Park Service.; New England Council.; New England Regional Planning Commission.; Philadelphia Regional Planning Federation.; Regional Plan Association (New York, N.Y.); Russell Sage Foundation.; Tennessee Valley Authority.; Town Planning Institute (London, England); United States Housing Corporation.; United States. Department of the Interior.; United States. Division of Subsistence Homesteads.; United States. Federal Emergency Relief Administration of Public Works.; United States. National Resources Committee.; United States. National Resources Planning Board.; United States. Resettlement Administration.; University of Pennsylvania -- Students.
Subjects:
City planning.; Community development, Urban.; Highway planning.; Housing.; Inland water transportation.; Landscape architecture.; Parks.; Railroads.; Regional planning.; Zoning.; City planners -- United States.; Landscape architects -- United States.; John Nolen Research Fund.
Places:
Bridgeport (Conn.) -- City planning.; Charlotte (N.C.) -- City planning.; Clearwater (Fla.) -- City planning.; Clewiston (Fla.) -- City planning.; Sarasota (Fla.) -- City planning.; Venice (Fla.) -- City planning.; Columbus (Ga.) -- City planning.; Johnson City (Tenn.) -- City planning.; Kingsport (Tenn.) -- City planning.; La Crosse (Wis.) -- City planning.; Madison (Wis.) -- City planning.; Lancaster (Pa.) -- City planning.; Reading (Pa.) -- City planning.; Little Rock (Ark.) -- City planning.; Mariemont (Ohio) -- City planning.; Niagara Falls (N.Y.) -- City planning.; Riverton (N.J.) -- City planning.; Roanoke (Va.) -- City planning.; Sacramento (Calif.) -- City planning.; San Diego (Calif.) -- City planning.; Boston (Mass.) -- City planning.; Spartanburg (S.C.) -- City planning.; Dubuque (Iowa) -- City planning.
Form and Genre Terms:
Blueprints.; Lecture notes.; Maps.; Photographs.; Negatives (photographic).; Scrapbooks.; Architectural drawings (visual works).; Diaries
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Pamphlets collected by Nolen can be found in the, John Nolen Pamphlet collection, #6337.
Justin Richardson Hartzog papers, #2407.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Control Documents and Inventories
Series II. Personal Files
Biographical Data
Schooling
Notes
Textbooks and Publications
Family Correspondence
Miscellaneous Personal Papers
Series III. Secretary to the American Society for the Extension of University Teaching
Series IV. Professional Career
Landscape Architect and City Planner
Routine Office Material
Policy Directives
Office Administration
Photographs
Card Files
Postcards
Project Material
Correspondence
Project Reports
Plans, Photographs, Negatives
Oversize Plans, Prints and Photostats
Educational Work in Planning, Lectures, Trusteeship
Other Professional Activities, and Public Works
Publications
Public Lectures Illustrated by Slides
Professional Associations
Travel for Professional Purposes
Competitions
Public Housing
Other Public Services, Conferences, Federal Government
Series V. Material About Nolen
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Control Documents and Inventories
  - Inventory of Glass Lantern Slides, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Catalogue of Books, Library of John Nolen, Cambridge Mass, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Negatives (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Possibly personal
  - Checklist of Negatives and Prints of Plans Prepared by the Office of John Nolen, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Special List - publications by Nolen, 1906 - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    bibliogrpahy
  - Personal clippings, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    News clippings regarding 'New Town for Old' book
  - List of John Nolen reports as Cataloged in office library, 1916 - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Plans Book, an Index of the Plans prepared by the office of John Nolen, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    only the index. no graphics.
  - Office of John Nolen Summaries of Selected Projects, 1937 - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Detailed summaries of his professional work - potential materials for the book
  - Lantern Slide Record - John Nolen (Box 90)
    Book. Listing of Slides divided into categories - A. City Approaches; B. Water Fronts; C. City Streets & Roads; D. Public Buildings; E. Small Open Spaces; F. Playgrounds; G. Parks and Parkways; H. City Planning; PR. Public Relations; K. Land Subdivisions; L.Housing; M.Historical Gardens; N. Large Private Places; O.Small; P. Universities; Q. Natural Scenery, Including National and State Parks; R. Landscape Paintings; S. Survey; Z. Inactive Slides
- Series II. Personal Files
  - Nolen Family Album, 1980 (Box 107, Folder 1)
    "A Record of Five Generations 1835-1954," compiled by John Nolen, Jr. and Barbara Nolen Strong
  - Biographical Data
    - Illustrated Lectures on City and Regional Planning and Related Subjects (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Biography, lecture flyer, lecture note cards
    - John Nolen, Background of a Pioneer Planner, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      [folder should be renamed] Booklet, newspaper clippings
    - News clippings, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Boston Authors Club. Bulletins, correspondence., 1936 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Prof. Organization
    - Book Research by Dana Doten. From D.D., 1936 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Professional
    - Book Research by Dana Doten. From J.N., 1936 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Harvard Tercentenary. correspondence, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      Personal
    - Political endorsements of Nolen. correspondence, 1932 - 1935 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      Proposal for Northern New England Parkway
    - Nolen Post 1937. Correspondence after Nolen's death., 1937 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Newspaper clippings. Walter Lippman - extracts from Boston Globe.Opinions on Nolen's planning work.
    - Newspaper clippings, loose & unfiled. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Presentation at the National Conference on City Planning, 1933 - 1935 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      Papers presented at the meeting. Follow-up correspondence.
    - Bibliography and references on city planning, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      Nolen's planning work / bibliography provided as references to York Chamber of Commerce in Pennsylvania
    - Biographical statement. Statements prepared for Who's Who and other publications., 1939 (Box 7, Folder 26)
      biography / written by others
    - Beta Theta Pi fraternity. correspondence, 1921 - 1923 (Box 7, Folder 29)
      House-warming Invitation letters and correspondence
  - Schooling
    - Notes
      - Schooling notes (Box 38)
        Most notes hand-written on 5x7" sheets of lined paper; some bound together, some loose. These were filed under six file cards labelled according to subject.
      - Landscape Architecture 0, November 7, 1904 (Box 38)
      - Horticulture 1a, 1903 (Box 38)
        Lecturer: B.M. Watson
      - Horticulture 2, 1904 (Box 38)
      - Planting and Transplanting, 1904 (Box 38)
      - Forestry 1, 1904 (Box 38)
      - Horticulture 1c, second term, 1905 (Box 38)
      - Horticulture 1c, second term, 1905 (Box 38)
      - Forestry 3, 1905 (Box 38)
      - Pure Design, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
        Lecturer: Dr. Denman Ross
      - Notes on Lecture of Dr. Denman Ross, "Pure Design". 2 copies., 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Herbaceous Plants, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Herbaceous Plants, first meeting after mid year, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Herbaceous Plants, first meeting after mid year, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Herbaceous Plants, second term, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Herbaceous Plants, second term, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Horticulture 1a, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Horticulture 1a, first lecture after exams, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Landscape Architecture i, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
        Lecturer: Olmsted & Shurtleff
      - Landscape Architecture II, 1903 - 1904 (Box 38)
      - Summary of Horticulture 1c, 1904 - 1905 (Box 38)
      - Architecture 2a, Summer 1903 (Box 38)
        Lecturer: Walter Dana Swan
      - Shrubs, second term (Box 38)
    - Textbooks and Publications
      - Girard College General Catalog, 1929 (Box 44)
        Catalog.
      - Girard College and Its Founder., 1853 (Box 44)
        Book.
      - The First Annual Report of the Directors of City Trusts, 1871 (Box 44)
        Book. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
      - The Fifth Annual Report of the Directors of City Trusts, 1875 (Box 44)
      - The Life and Character of Stephen Girard, 1887 (Box 44)
        Book. Written by Henry Atlee Ingram, LL.B. with an Appendix Descriptive of Girard College.
      - The Record '93, 1893 (Box 44)
        Book. The Record of the Class of 1893 University of Pennsylvania (2 copies)
      - Record: 1893-98 of the Class of '93, 1893 (Box 44)
        Book. The University of Pennsylvania Published by the Class of Philadelphia (4 copies)
      - Course of Study for Eight Years, 1894 (Box 44)
        Book. Girard College
      - Pennsylvania Songs, 1896 (Box 44)
        Book. A collection of college songs, glees, and choruses generally in use among students and alumni of the University of Pennsylvania
      - Statue of Stephen Girard, 1897 (Box 44)
        Book. Records of its erection and unveiling
      - Semi-Centennial Anniversary of Girard College, 1898 (Box 44)
        Book. Biographical sketch of Stephen Girard, his will, and other papers relating to the college and its development and government
      - Course of Study for Eight Years, 1904 (Box 44)
      - "A History of The Philomathean Society of The University of Pennsylvania", 1913 (Box 44)
        Book. Published on the 100th Anniversary of the founding of the Philomathean Society, University of Pennsylvania
      - "History of Girard College", 1927 (Box 44)
        Book. Girard College, Given to Nolen by author, inscription in front (June 15, 1927)
      - The Class of '93 Record to 1930, 1930 (Box 44)
        Book. A history of The University of Pennsylvania Class of 1893 history through 1930 compiled by Louis Barcroft Runk (Chairman of the Record Committee).
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Pupils, 1930 (Box 44)
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Pupils, 1931 (Box 44)
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Pupils, 1932 (Box 44)
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Pupils, 1933 (Box 44)
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Pupils, 1934 (Box 44)
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Pupils, 1935 (Box 44)
      - President's Report, 1935 (Box 44)
        Book. Girard College (Draft Copy with handwritten notes)
      - President's Report and Catalogue of Students, 1936 (Box 44)
        Book. Girard College, 2 copies
      - Catalogue and Announcements, 1890 - 1891 (Box 44)
        Book. University of Pennsylvania
      - Catalogue and Announcements, College Department, 1890 - 1891 (Box 44)
      - Catalogue and Announcements, 1892 - 1893 (Box 44)
      - Catalogue and Announcements, College Department, 1892 - 1893 (Box 44)
      - President's Report, 1910 - 1913 (Box 44)
      - Educational Setting of Stephen Girard's Benefaction, 1902 (Box 44)
        Program. An Address Delivered by Martin G. Brumbaugh, Ph.D., Professor of Pedagogy in The University of Pennsylvania given on Founder's Day in the Chapel of Girard College
      - Founder's Day Address by Henry Kraemer, Ph.D., 1912 (Box 44)
        Program. Presentation of the Stephen Girard Chronological Tablet by the Girard College Alumni (May 20, 1912)
      - Addresses at the Inauguration of Merle Middleton Odgers, Ph.D. As President of Girard College, 1936 (Box 44)
        Program. Girard College
      - "Political History of the United States", 1889 (Box 44)
        Textbook. Outline of the lectures delivered before the Junior class, Wharton School, Department of American History, University of Pennsylvannia, By John Bach McMaster
      - "A History of The United States for Schools", 1889 (Box 45)
        Book. With maps, plans, illustrations, and questions
      - University Extension: Has it a Future?, 1890 (Box 45)
        Book. By H.J. Mackinder, M.A. and Michael E. Sadler, M.A.
      - "The Renaissance: The Revival of Learning and Art in the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Centuries", 1891 (Box 45)
        Book. By Philip Schaff, D.D., LL.D.
      - "Eighteen Years of University Extension", 1891 (Box 45)